(With English accent)
"Renstjärnas gata thirty-one?"
Thirty-one. Renstjärnas gata?
It's right over there!
But dear child! What a mess!
What will dad say when he sees this?
Sit there.
No! I just told you!
Don't soil the nice dress that mommy has bought!
It was so clean and nice.
Sit still and watch the other children play.
No!
If you are acting like this -
we're headed straight home!
You are getting dirty all the time.
We are going home to bed.
All done.
- Hey!
- Hello.
Fill it up.
Help!
- Is somebody calling for help?
- It's always a racket around here.
- Heeeelp!
- What hoodlums are they?
I don't know. They're always at it.
Don't pour the gas in my pocket!
Help... Help!
You goddamn...
Help! I've broke my leg! Help!
- Boys!
- Wino!
Help!
Help! I'm stuck!
(In Finnish)
- Who is that?
- He's asking for help
(In Finnish)
- Noo.. No, we can't help him.
I'm stuck.. I've fallen.. Help!
(Swedish student graduation song)
Help!
Thanks.
- Hey! You!
- Hey buddy!
- My leg is broken
- Heeey!
- You have a drink!
- No, thanks. My foot hurts so bad.
(Singing)
In the spring sun
You're going to meet my old lady! -
If she can trust you.
My foot hurts so bad. I live over here. -
Can you please help me?
Your foot hurts? You shouldn't be -
walking around then! Just a second...
I'll help you. If I could just... Oh!
This is no good! I've got to get some help!
- If I can have the balloon.
- Of course. Here. Please get some help.
Heeelp! Heeelp!
Help... Help!
Uh... Look at that. This is tire-some. Heh.
- Nice weather tonight.
- I think my foot is broken.
Can you help me?
Gosh! Your leg is broken and you're stuck!
Of course we will help you.
I live just up here.
- How can I help?
- I'm stuck.
- Pull!
- Remove that tire.
- Oh hey!
- Careful!
- Careful.
- I can turn around.
- There!
- Yes, there.
Mind your foot.
- I'll run and get an ambulance!
- Yes, do that!
- There, this is good. This is all right.
- I'll help you.
- Thanks.
- There, there.
- Shall I take the hat?
- Thanks.
- Are you all right?
- Please sitt, miss. In the couch.
Thank you.
I guess it's the nursing home from now on.
- What time is it?
- The time?
- A quarter past two.
- A handsome watch.
It chimes too.
I got it from my father today.
I got a similar clock by my father once.
But I gave it away to a beautiful girl.
- It's called something else...
- Can you ask Herbert about that?
No, he's in bed. He was asleep. He didn't hear me there.
- Hey, you.
- Hey.
- May I sit by the window?
- Yes.
- Is this all right?
- Yes. Thank you, nurse. Thanks.
Out of an Old Mans Head
Drawing and animation
Assistants
Script
The old man
Featuring
Directed by
Tage Danielsson
Production
Art director
Out of an Old Mans Head
What nasty weather.
Look at that rain.
It was better in my time...
When I was a child -
We had sun!
I just have to close my eyes -
to see it.
The skies were so blue!
And the sun -
It was yellow.
And the grass -
was green.
Well, brownish green I guess...
We had some lovely summers back then!
Lisa and Jörgen and Tore...
Oh, boy.. Oh boy...
How scared we were of the bull
Magnus, was his name. Magnus number two!
He was a nasty beast. Scary!
Dad was a blacksmith.
He was... Strong.
Mom. Oh, mom was so sweet.
She was the best.
She was always so happy
and always so merry
Cinnamon! I remember she had it in...
And almonds and...
And butter!
And Jörgen, he was...
That was... Those were good times.
Mom...
Mom was... Mom was kind and good hearted.
It not like I ever got any higher education
I found it hard!
I went to the village school
Miss Kvist
Mother!
Mo-th-er.
(Swedish psalm about summer)
Oh, those summers...
Evert pushed me under the surface...
Evert, he was a bully
He was mean, Evert.
But Everts sister, she was cute...
Oh, boy. Oh, boy...
I was a gentleman already then
Already in those days.
Oh, yeah. Well that was...
I wasn't stupid, you know.
She fell for it.
Love...
It was the summer of my confirmation
What's his name? Wallin or Wallinder...
The priest.
Wallin, I think.
It was Wallin...
Yes, his name was Wallin.
I had a new suit and it all...
There were more celebrations back then.
She was so cute, I was...
I was lost in...
She was terribly cute.
And Evert, he...
Always Evert!
But she was mean. Just as her brother.
Family strains.
Dad was furious. Of course.
It was a scandal.
In a small place like that.
When he crept up...
All the rabbits bursted out...
Not rabbits! Hens!
They fled
I remember exactly what I had in my pack -
the day when I ran away...
Away to the big city.
The pen knife and half a loaf of bread -
and the hymnbook I got when grandma died.
And the comb and the watch -
and three eggs and the photo of mom.
And an aneline pen -
and twelve meat balls.
Yeah, I'll never forget moms meatballs!
She made really good meat balls. Yes, she did.
They were one part beef and one part pork
I remember that. And eggs, of course.
And breadcrumbs -
and salt and pepper.
I think that was all.
And a splash of cream!
She knew how to cook meat balls. Yes, sir.
I munched away. They were wonderful!
Oh, and onion! I forgot onion.
I got a job at Holmbergs Construction.
I was to carry tiles -
and beer...
to the foreman.
Stora Brogatan 38 was the first building.
I remember thinking there were so many floors.
His name was Lind -
but they called him Spuling.
I don't know why.
The entire spring and autumn.
And the summer in between, of course.
I rented a room on Södermalm -
on Svartensgatan.
It was a bit lonely.
He was a widower, foreman Lind.
He cooked his food himself.
He cooked and salted a leg of mutton -
with the fur on.
It lasted him all winter
and he shared some too.
It was a cold winter, the first one.
Stora Brogatan 40.
Stora Brogatan 42.
The one one the corner.
I belive we started with it in the spring.
Come here...
Sven - I think he was my best friend.
He borrowed me a pair of pants once.
Well.. I haven't seen him for a long time.
I heard he became a sea captain eventually.
I remember when we were at the amusement park.
It was Sven and me...
...and that skinny boy from Värmland.
Oh, what was his name again?
The skinny boy, I think he was from Grums.
What the hell was his name again?
And.. Where was it that he was working?
I think it was a mechanical workshop -
somewhere on Södermalm.
Ah... What was his name...
He was from Värmland, yes he was.
He was from Grums.
His name was...
It was... He was...
Åstr... No.
He was strong, yes he was.
What the hell was his name?
That I can't remember a thing like that.
His name was...
Oh...
His name... was...
He was living on Renstjärnasgatan...
Somewhere in that area...
Why can't I remember his name?
Am I getting senile?
His name was...
Björn Åberg was his name! That's it!
That was my first real bender, that night.
Oh, boy... Young and wild...
And then that night in Vaxholm.
Boy, how embarrassed I was.
We went out there, a bunch of us -
and I met this girl there...
Her name was Els-Marie -
or Elsa-Marie... She was a cute one!
I was a lovely night. The birds were singing.
But I had such gasses -
I never seen the likes of it.
I was young but with a moustasche!
To be handsome.
Then I saw a tin can and figured -
if I go kick it and pass some gas -
she won't notice!
I missed it. I was devastated.
It was...
Björk... Björk...
Björk must not mutter for himself.
Björk shall get some medicin.
This will buck him up.
This medicine makes you spry.
We'll have to take it every day.
Can't a man just sit here and think?
I don't think it's good for Björk -
to sit here and brood by himself.
- There.
- Crap.
I'll be right back and get Björk to the others.
Björk... Björk... Björk...
This medicine makes you spry.
We'll have to take it every day.
I've got an idea!
A bottle of whisky should fit in three bottles of medicine.
This is good.
It should be possible to systemize it -
like chain letters!
Yes!
Just like a chain letters!
Yes, this is great!
But with a message in the bottle.
Then I'd have to start with -
writing a letter.
A letter to the other geezers.
To John Andersson.
Then I'd put Bock as number two -
And Svensson and Arvid Kling -
And Gustavsson and Anna.
Yes, Anna should be in on it too -
She is so kind.
And I'd put myself in last.
Yes, that's right.
And then... Let me see...
Then I'd have to write to Sven -
and to that other... Björn...
What's his name? Yes, Åberg! From Värmland.
And Harald Viktorin.
And wrap them up.
And then it's up to the post office.
And they will cross over the name -
on top and put their own name last.
And there will be mail to John.
And he'll say that he received medicine.
Then they'll get three people each -
who'll send a bottle of medicine each.
To Bocken, yes that's it.
That will be... Three times nine is twenty-seven.
And then...
Three times seven is twenty-one.
Eighty-one.
That's null.. three...
Two hundred and fourty...
Not bad! We're already up to loads!
So, let's see... Three... Nine it is.
And then... Two.. Oh, yes. And one residue.
That will be sevenhundred and twenty-nine.
And then it's my turn!
It's me!
Two thousand hundred and eighty-seven bottles!
I hope John doesn't get mad when he only gets three.
And I'll have all the deposit.
That'll be lots of money.
After all, it was my idea.
Then I'll buy myself a new hat -
and a pair of shoes.
And maybe a fur coat.
And I should have a top hat.
That would not be bad at all!
I guess it will be my time soon too.
Phew. No, it can't be like that.
Seems gloomy that too...
Björk. Björk!
Wake up, Björk!
Is he dreaming again?
Get hold of yourself, Björk.
It's stopped raining and it's time to air.
Björk may move to the kitchen.
Sit and think...
Hello, nurse.
Björk has got a letter -
all the way from America.
What.. Oh? What is it?
A letter for me?
I haven't got a letter for a long time...
Who can it be from?
Who can it be that writes to me -
from America?
"Dear..."
"Dear Father."
- Shall I help Björk to read the letter?
- No, thanks.
"Dear..."
- Yes, please.
- Well, then.
It must be from my son Erik.
He is in America.
I haven't seen him -
in thirty-fourty years...
"Dear father."
"Finally you'll get a letter from your negligent son."
"It was many years ago that I got in touch with you" -
- "but I've been meaning to write many times" -
"but there has always something in between."
"Me and my wife now have two sons" -
"that now are seven and ten years old."
"Named John and William."
"As I wrote, I remarried after the war"-
"and now I'm very happy with my beloved Mary Elisabeth."
"We have moved west from Jacksonville to lndiana."
The wild west.
"The moving was a cumbersome process" -
"but the children enjoyed the trip. For them it was like an adventure."
"We live in the outskirts of Indianapolis"...
- lndianapolis?
- I don't know how it's pronounced.
..."lndianapolis is the capital of lndiana."
"And we've bought us a beautiful home here."
"It's not big, but it's enough for our needs."
"Especially Mary Elisabeth is happy here, as her heritage is from this city" -
"any many of her relatives live who are Quakers"
- What?
- "Quakers, which I've become as well"
- Oh?
- "I work here in a 'factori' as a gunsmith"
"I like it here and get along well with my work mates."
"Life goes on and nothing out of the ordinary."
"But a month ago the president" -
"was here for an electoral meeting."
"He paid our 'factori' a visit too" -
"and shook peoples hands, including my own."
"He was a very nice gentleman who spoke common and natural" -
"It is a beautiful area where we live" -
"and the wild and untamed nature is just around the corner."
"A friend of mine, George Kaminski, and me" -
"sometimes on sundays go hunting to a lake" -
"Lake Monroe is its name, and often we come home with a rabbit" -
"or a wild 'duck' for dinner."
A 'duck'? What is that? That's strange.
"Well, that was a few lines of how we are over here."
"Everything had been well" -
"if not Mary Elisabeth had fallen ill" -
"and have to go to the 'hospitalet'."
What? The 'hospitalet'? (= asylym)
"It's nothing that you have to worry about."
"It's a simple procedure of gallstone" -
"but the hospital costs a lot of money over here" -
"and therefor I ask if you could lend me 500 dollars for this purpose."
"I hope you can help me with this and that all is well."
"Best 'regards' from Mary Elisabeth and John and William."
"From your beloved son Erik F. Bjoerk."
Oh, but wasn't that was fun, Björk -
to get a letter all the way from America?
Now we'll head over to the main room -
and listen to the evening service.
- I can drive myself.
- No bother at all.
- There, Björk.
- Have you got a letter, Johan?
- What?
Yes, from my son Erik in America.
You have a boy in America?
I didn't know that.
Oh yes. He is head of a gun factory over there.
- He knows the president as well.
- I'll be damned!
Can't you at least be quiet during the service?
What have you done with your life?
When the day comes -
can you tell the mighty one:
"This is what I have done with my life."
"I have been a good man."
Amen.
We will now sing psalm 265.
Well, this is what I've done with my life.
A hell of a lot of houses.
Slaving away.
And now it all has to go.
They're just wrecking and wrecking,
That was it.
I was working with Viktorssons then.
And at Nostins.
I remember that.
I was twenty-five when I was there.
Oh, well. Oh, well...
You're always out drinking
Everything has to go...
I never get any money...
I've been a good man. Yeah, right.
I never get any money!
You're just out drinking!
You never play with little Erik!
You don't care about me!
You've stolen from my tobacco, you rascal.
Yes you have!
Bah. Don't lie for your father.
You've stolen tobacco!
You! Confess!
Damn scoundrel. Confess!
Are you lying me straight in the face?
Maj! Come here!
What is it? You don't want me anything?
- Look here.
- No!
Erik ran further away than I did.
All the way to America.
And then he was gone.
And Maj went belly up in -42. That was it.
Phew...
And after that it's been lonely.
That was the service. -
Now the senior citizens talk show.
(Jingle)
A senior citizen is merry -
remembers good times with no worry.
Ain't nobody want to listen -
to that mumbo jumbo.
Well, that was fun...
- Hey, let's go to your room.
- Yes, we might as well.
- Nurse Ester?
- Nurse Alice? We'd like to move.
Careful. There.
- So, you've got a boy in America?
- Yes, he's a big man there.
I'll be right back. I'll just get my bag.
Oh, nurse Ester? Would nurse mind helping me -
send five hundred dollars to my boy in America?
He's lent me so much money and I'd like to pay him back.
My bank book is in that drawer.
- Of course, I'd arrange that tomorrow.
- Most kind of you.
Thank you so much. That would be very kind.
- There! Rise and shine!
- Uh! Oh! Careful!
Thank you.
Thanks, thanks.
Thank you so much.
- That was good.
- Shall we get some water?
- Good night.
- Night, night.
- Some water, there.
- There you are.
- Thank you.
- Good night.
"Good night, darling."
- Maybe you could unlock this?
- Of course, I'll just...
(Written on bag)
May not be opened until my passing away. Johan
If I can find the key hole.
So, you got a boy in America?
Oh, yes. He's a big man there.
He knows the president.
I'm going to send him five hundred dollars.
- That is what I'm going to do.
- I went to the park today.
Oh?
The tulips are yellow this year.
Have the swans arrived?
I was looking at the building lot.
It's going to be a library.
Yes, they are just wrecking and wrecking.
Houses that have been there for hundreds of years.
Wrecking and wrecking -
and then that goddamn concrete.
It will never last.
No, I didn't see any swans.
But I had a piece of bread with me.
I gave it to the doves.
Soon there won't be a single man who knows -
how to build a proper tile wall.
Big boxes, all of them. In my days -
you learned the trade from the beginning.
- Well...
- Well, cheers then, Johan.
Cheers to you, Sven.
Ah! Good water, this!
By the way, I cut out an ad from the paper today.
Just wait and hear.
"Amazing extra incomes."
"You can make 250 kronors a week" -
"by tying mats in your own home" -
with ths. new spect. methd."
I was thinking we might start up a little industry.
- You, me and maybe Johan.
- You think so?
But it says that -
you have to buy a machine -
and some yarn and such.
Do you really think your boy in America -
needs all that money?
Yes, yes, no, no!
My savings are not touched for this!
But hey, I have another idea -
that could bring some money.
A kind of chain letter, with whisky in medicin bottles
that is sent to all old geezers and old ladies.
In a few weeks we could make -
several thousand kronors. What'd you say?
- That wasn't bad at all. Cheers!
- Cheers.
And then we move out from here.
We go travel somewhere.
- We could go to Stockholm, right?
- Talking to me about Stockholm...
I've build half that city, oh yes.
And hey, then we'll go do some fine dining!
And then we'll go to Västerlånggatan 24.
That's where you'll find some ladies, see.
That's one hot place!
I had to run from the establishment without pants!
- Cheers!
- You've sure been around, Johan.
Oh, yeah. That's something else than this hole.
- And then we go to America!
- Yes! We'll go stay with your son!
Oh, yes. No problems.
He's got a big mansion among the indians.
How lucky that I'm educating myself then.
"I am a boy. You are a girl."
That's great!
You can talk to the indians!
That's really damn great.
Can I borrow your book? That is great!
- Cheers to that. Thanks and good night.
- Cheers.
- Hey?
- Yeah?
- It's not really too bad here, after all.
- Oh, no, no. "Good night, darling."
Good night.
Oh well.
Of all the colors true most beautiful is the blue
Blue is the color of the mighty sky
where nothing clouds the sun shine
Allelian-lian, allelian-lian-
- allelian-lian, harmony
Hadderian-rian, hadderian-rian
- addelian-lian, harmony.